Wait until Your Majesty
폐하께서 사현을 내놓을 때까지
Surrenders Xie Xuan, then he'll come
시간을 끌다가 오면
By then
나중에
No one can fault him
누가 그의 잘못을 따지겠습니까
Enough
됐네
My general
짐의 장군인데
If I use him
믿고
I trust him
써줘야지
Order Zhu Yuanzhi
주원지를 불러서
To rescue the emperor
지원하게 하라
Yes
예
The 21st year of Longwu
융무 21년
Zhu Yuanzhi led troops to rescue the emperor
주원지는 군을 이끌고 지원에 나서고
In less than half a month
보름도 안 되어
He pierced through the western aristocratic coalition
서쪽의 사족 연합군을 물리치고
Then launched a lightning strike on the southern commander's camp
그 다음 신속히 남쪽 장군 군영을 들이쳐
Personally beheaded the rebel general
반란군 두목의 목을 칩니다.
The eastern route scattered like birds and beasts upon hearing the news
이에 동쪽 반란군은 놀라서 뿔뿔이 흩어지고
The great families submitted memorials begging for mercy
사족들은 살려달라고 상소문을 올립니다.
Zhu Yuanzhi
주원지
The rebels are now pacified
난은 이미 평정됐는데
Why aren't you wearing court robes?
왜 조복 대신 갑옷을 입고
Wearing armor in court
대전에 든 건가
Right
그러게
This is
거참
Well said
옳은 말씀입니다
Otherwise, Minister Wang
그럼 왕 대인이 나 대신
How about going to the front to fight for me?
전방에 나가 싸우는 건 어떻겠습니까
In the court
여긴 조당일세
General Zhu, please be careful with your words
주 장군은 말을 삼가게
Don't think
당신들이 뒤에서
I don't know how you
나를 어찌 말하는지
Talk about me behind my back
내가 모를 줄 알아요
If not for concern for Your Majesty's safety
폐하의 안위만 아니었어도
Would I have rushed through the night
내가 밤새 말을 달려
To save you gossiping women?
이간질한 당신들을 구했을 것 같아요
You
아니
And some of you
그리고 당신들끼리
I don't care how you fight behind the scenes
암투를 벌이든 말든 상관없는데
Whoever dares involve Your Majesty
감히 폐하를 끌어들이면
Better think carefully
각오하는 게 좋은 겁니다
Who has such great resentment?
누가 이렇게 화를 내나
Kowtow to Your Majesty
폐하를 뵙습니다
You've worked hard
수고했네
General Zhu
주 장군
Your Majesty is well
폐하만 무사하시면
I am not tired
소신은 수고랄 게 없습니다
Read
읽어라
General Zhu Yuanzhi of Zhenbei
진북장군 주원지는
Loyalty and courage bestowed by heaven
충직하고 용맹하며
Merits illustrious
군공이 혁혁하다
Rescued the emperor and quelled rebellion
군주를 도와 난을 평정하여
Merit surpassing all officials
공이 누구보다 크니
Now specially promoted to Grand General
오늘 대장군에 책봉하고
Envoy with credentials, bearer of the Yellow Axe
최고 군사 권력을 부여하며
Commander of all military affairs
일체 군정을 맡긴다
Granted the Nine Bestowments as special honor
공훈대신만 누리는 최고 예우로 대하고
May enter court without hurrying
조당에서 무릎 꿇지 않으며
Addressed without name
이름 대신 관직으로 불리고
May wear sword and shoes in court
검을 차고 대전에 들며
Opened a ministry equal to the Three Excellencies
관직은 개부의동삼사로 한다
I
성은이
Kowtow in gratitude for Your Majesty's grace
망극하옵니다